One Pace Premium Keep the project alive: ko-fi.com/not6ip
One Pace Premium Keep the project alive: ko-fi.com/not6ip
Hold it, Paulie!
Arrête-toi, Pauly !
You won't get away this time!
Cette fois, tu t'échapperas pas !
And I'm asking you to wait just a bit longer!
Je veux juste un petit délai, je vous dis !
Who's that?
Que se passe-t-il ?
That's Paulie.
C'est Pauly.
He's running from debt collectors again.
– Il a encore des créanciers aux trousses. – Rembourse-nous !
Like I said, I don't have any cash today!
Puisque je vous dis que j'ai rien sur moi !
That's not gonna cut it!
Arrête ton char ! Tu t'en tireras pas comme ça !
Damn, they won't let up!
Bon sang, ce qu'ils sont collants.
Huh? Perfect! Yagara bulls!
Des Yagaras ! Sauvé !
Rope Action!
Rope Action !
He's a Galley-La shipwright!
C'est un gars de Galley-La Company !
Sorry, but I'd like to borrow one of your yagaras for a bit!
Désolé, les mecs, je vais avoir besoin d'un Yagara !
Round Turn!
Round Turn !
The Case of the Kidnapped Pirate
Kidnapping
Damn! He got away again!
Bon sang ! Il a encore réussi à filer !
Well then, everyone, take care!
À la revoyure, les gars ! Portez-vous bien !
Let's run around again soon!
Faudra qu'on se refasse un jogging, un de ces quatre !
Dammit!
Et merde...
Seriously though! You came in the nick of time!
Pauly Contremaître gréement et mât Quai n°1 Galley-La Company
Paulie Rigging and Mast Foreman Dock One Galley-La Company
Eh ben... T'es vraiment tombé à pic, toi.
What a relief! He's one of your shipwrights, right?
Ouf, sauvés... C'est un gars de chez vous, hein ?
That's right.
Tout à fait !
Hey! Thanks!
Ohé ! Merci du coup de main !
That money belongs to us!
Cet argent est à nous !
What? Money?
Hein ? De l'argent ?
Let's see...
Ah, il parle de ça ?
Hey...! Huh? Hey!
Ohé ! Oh... Ohé...
Get back here!
Reviens !
That jerk!
L'enfoiré ! Je vais le choper !
I got this.
Je m'en occupe.
What? A... A pigeon?
Hein ? Un... Un pigeon ?
Ow, ow, ow, ow, ow! Hey, hey, let me go!
Aïe... C'est bon, lâche-moi !
What the hell are you doing?!
Qu'est-ce qui te prend, bon sang ?
I'm not gonna run, man! I get it, okay?!
Je vais pas m'enfuir, je te dis. T'es bouché, ou quoi ?
Let go of my ear!
Lâche mon oreille !
Rob Lucci Sawyer and Treenail Foreman Dock One Galley-La Company
Rob Lucci Contremaître Gournable et Scieur Quai n°1 Galley-La Company
Here I was lucky enough to find all this money just now...!
Dire que j'avais enfin décroché le gros lot !
You'll regret this, Lucci!
Tu me paieras ça, Lucci !
Don't pay back your debts with other people's money, you ignoramus!
On ne rembourse pas ses dettes avec l'argent d'autrui. Bougre d'idiot !
But I found this money!
Je l'ai trouvé, cet argent !
You think that story will fly?!
Encore cette histoire ?
It just happened to be on the yagara that I borrowed!
Puisque je te dis que j'ai choisi ce Yagara au pif !
They're back.
Les revoilà.
Well, I'm happy for you, Usopp!
Tout est bien qui finit bien, Usopp.
Don't act like you've got no skin in the game! It's our 200 million belly!
Je te retiens, toi ! Y avait 200 Millions dans ces valises !
That's right! Why the hell weren't you the first one to go get it back?!
Il a raison !
But that pigeon said he'd go.
Bah oui, le piaf a dit qu'il s'en chargeait.
Well... I'm sorry.
Écoutez, nous sommes désolés.
We should deal with our own idiot employees...
Permettez-nous de punir cet idiot nous-mêmes.
otherwise, it'd create undue tension if you'd caught him.
Vous le laisser pourrait envenimer les choses.
Well, consider yourselves lucky your money wasn't stolen by the Franky Family.
Et puis, voyons le bon côté des choses, la Franky Family repart bredouille.
Hmm... That's true, but...
Oui, c'est vrai, mais...
Yeah, that's true, that's true.
Ouais, pluche que chûr...
So then, who were those weird-looking guys from earlier?
Dites, c'est qui au juste, cette bande d'énergumènes ?
The Franky Family is a group of ship dismantlers.
Les membres de la Franky Family désossent les navires.
Dismantlers? They seemed more like thugs than honest craftsmen.
Ils les désossent ?
Right. They're also bounty hunters on the side.
En effet, à leurs heures perdues, ils sont également chasseurs de primes.
They cause quite the stir every time they discover pirates have entered the city.
Dès qu'ils voient des pirates en ville, ils s'en prennent à eux.
They're a public nuisance.
Ils nous causent bien du tort.
If they take out the pirates who come to town, they also get their ship, see?
Une fois l'équipage neutralisé en ville, ils filent s'emparer du navire.
They dismantle the ship and sell the usable lumber.
Une fois désossé, ils revendent les matériaux utilisables.
What crawled up their butts?! Are they trying to dismantle all pirate crews?!
Quelle bande de canailles ! Sans navire, il n'y a plus d'équipage !
Well, run afoul of them and not even your bones will remain.
De toute façon, on ne retrouve ni l'un ni l'autre.
But they didn't look that strong.
Ils n'ont pas l'air bien balèzes, pourtant.
They're just lackeys.
Ceux-là n'étaient que des sous-fifres.
Think what you will of them, but never underestimate their devoted boss, Franky.
Mais le chef de la famille, c'est une tout autre histoire.
We got him, Mr. Iceburg.
Voici notre homme, monsieur Icebarg.
Again, you're hurting my ear!
Tu me fais mal, je te dis !
Good work, Lucci.
Merci du coup de main, Lucci.
We're sorry this birdbrain caused you trouble.
Hattori Pigeon de Lucci
Hattori Lucci's Pigeon
Excusez cette imbécile pour son comportement stupide.
Ah! It spoke again!
Il cause encore !
Now, apologize to them, Paulie!
Allez ! Excuse-toi, Pauly !
That pigeon's doing all the talking!
Il fait que jacter, ce pigeon !
It's like he's speaking for the guy with the hat.
Il parle à la place du gars, on dirait.
In any case, I'm so glad the money's back!
Enfin bon, content d'avoir récupéré l'argent.
Hey, so the money belonged to you?
Alors comme ça, il est à vous ?
I brought it back for you.
Vous pouvez me remercier.
Oh, thanks!
Ouais, merci.
Thank me with finder's fee of ten percent.
Filez-moi 10 %, et on n'en parle plus.
Sorry 'bout that, sir.
Excusez-le, chers clients.
This guy's gambling debt is so high, he's turned greedy and forgot his manners.
Ce crétin est criblé de dettes de jeu.
Okay, but why are you talking?!
Mais comment ça se fait que tu causes, toi ?
You cagey bastard! Stop running your mouth, Lucci!
Espèce d’empaffé... Tu l'ouvres trop, Lucci.
Rope Action:
Rope Action !
Bowline Knot!
Nœud de chaise !
Discipline:
Châtiment !
Wait! Oh, no! He's serious!
Arrêtez ! Vous allez le tuer !
Fly Fishing!
Pêche au gros !
Well, this always happens.
Rassurez-vous, il est habitué.
He absorbed the impact with just one arm!
Il a absorbé l'impact d'une seule main !
Wh-What kind of fingers does he have?
Il a des doigts en acier, ou quoi ?
What sort of shipwrights do they have working here?
Bon sang, d'où ils sortent, les charpentiers d'ici ?
Hey! You, with the goggles!
Hé, toi ! Le gars aux lunettes !
Huh?
Hein ?
Hey, think about it carefully.
Réfléchis un peu, tu veux.
The only one who ever mocked or provoked you
Celui qui s'est foutu de toi et qui t'a provoqué...
was that pigeon!
C'est le pigeon !
Okay, but...
Ça, je m'en balance. Celui qui m'a frappé, c'est Lucci.
The pigeon can't hit you himself, so he had that guy do it!
C'est parce que le pigeon pouvait pas le faire lui-même !
Hey, pigeon!
Hé, le pigeon !
Fight your own battles!
Si tu veux te battre, fais-le toi-même !
Say something!
Dis quelque chose !
Oh? You wanna fight? Bring it on, you bastard!
Tu veux te battre ? Allez, amène-toi !
Stop it, Paulie.
Arrête ça, Pauly.
I'm Rob L– N-No, I mean, Hattori the pigeon.
Je suis Rob... Euh, non... Je veux dire, Hattori le pigeon.
And this is Rob Lucci, one of the workers here. Nice to meet you!
Et voici Rob Lucci. Il travaille ici. Enchantés ! Rouhou !
Oh? He just about introduced himself as if he were the human!
Tiens ? Un peu plus, et ce pigeon allait se présenter comme un humain.
Whoa! Seriously?! Then you really were the one mocking him!
Non, sérieux ? Alors c'est toi qui causais !
You're really, really good! I didn't notice!
T'es trop fort ! J'y avais vu que du feu !
Stop. Don't make a big deal of it.
Arrêtez d'applaudir. Il n'y a vraiment pas de quoi. Rouhou !
He's a weirdo who can't talk to people normally.
Cette andouille est trop coincée pour parler normalement.
Wait a sec! What's up with you, lady?!
Minute ! C'est quoi, cette fille ?
Who... me?
Pardon ?
What a hussy!
Quelle indécence.
Huh?
Hein ?
You're showing off your legs way too much!
Comment oses-tu te trimballer les jambes à l'air ?
This is a workplace for men! What possessed you to dress like that?!
C'est un chantier d'hommes, ici ! C'est pas une tenue convenable !
Now, Paulie, calm down.
Allons, Pauly ! Calme toi.
You too, Kalifa!
Toi aussi, Kalifa ?
You should know better than to wear scandalous clothes!
Tu t'obstines encore à jouer les aguicheuses ?
How many times do I have to tell you?! Wear pants! Long pants!
Combien de fois t'ai-je dit qu'il fallait mettre un pantalon ?
What the heck...?
– C'est quoi, le souci ? – Un pantalon ?
He's a weirdo too!
Lui aussi, il est taré !
Well, that was fun. Let's open the gate and head inside.
Allons, ça suffit. Ouvrez plutôt les portes, qu'on entre.
Hard to believe the size of this gate! And it's manually operated?!
Non mais, vous avez vu la taille de ces deux portes ?
Can those two weirdos open it by themselves?
Ces deux gars vont y arriver ?
Whoa! It's moving!
J'y crois pas, elles bougent !
Well, each dock has only five shipwright foremen.
Malgré leurs airs, ils font partie des cinq contremaîtres
Strange as they are, their skills earned them their spots as Dock One foremen.
assez talentueux pour travailler sur ce quai.
Kaku, the man from earlier, is one of them.
Tout comme Kaku, que vous avez vu auparavant.
What matters in this world is how one plies their trade.
Ici, seul le savoir-faire compte.
They're weird, but so what?
Ne faites pas attention à leur côté farfelu.
Yeah, they are weird.
Farfelu, c'est le terme.
Ah! It's starting to open!
Ah, c'est ouvert !
And keep hold of your money. There shouldn't be thieves here, but still...
Cette fois, gardez votre argent à l'œil. Le chantier est sûr, mais bon...
Well, it's partially my fault. Sorry for the trouble.
Compris.
Hey, Luffy!
– Hé, Luffy ! – Quoi ?
Make sure you guard me good!
Il me faut une protection rapprochée !
Okay, don't worry! Leave it to me!
OK, pigé ! Compte sur moi !
I'm worried.
J'ai peur.
Leave it to me!
Compte sur moi.
What you see here is Dock One, the core of Galley-La Company,
Le quai n°1 est celui où travaillent nos meilleurs éléments.
where we handle our most challenging orders.
On y gère les projets les plus délicats.
Here, come inside.
Je vous en prie, entrez.
– Wow!
Ouah !
Whoa!
Ouaaaah !
Wow! It's all huge!
Ouaaaah ! C'est gigantesque !
This shipyard's even more incredible when seen up close!
C'est vraiment impressionnant de voir un chantier naval en vrai.
Yeah!
– Ouais ! – Tu l'as dit.
There're so many craftsmen.
Ça grouille d'artisans.
Now, this way.
Par ici, s'il vous plaît.
Oh, it's Mr. Iceburg!
Tiens ! Voilà m'sieur Icebarg !
Hey! The boss is here!
Hé, les gars ! Le patron nous rend visite !
Good morning, Mr. Iceburg!
M'sieur Icebarg !
Good morning!
Bien le bonjour !
Boss! Could you take a look at how the hull turned out?
Patron ! Vous pourrez venir jeter un œil au bordé ?
Sure! I'll come by later!
Oui, tout à l'heure.
Nice day today, Mr. Iceburg!
Heureux de vous voir, m'sieur Icebarg.
Well, hi there. Everything going well?
Oui, moi de même. Tout se passe bien ?
Yes, sir! They're going pretty well!
Ouais ! Ça roule au poil !
Whoa! Everyone likes Iceboss.
Eh bah, il a la cote, le père Icebarg.
Indeed they do. Skill means everything in this city.
Évidemment. Dans cette cité, le talent prime.
Shipbuilding has always been this island's main industry,
Autrefois, voyez-vous, cette île réputée pour ses chantiers navals
and seven shipyards were competing for contracts.
abritait sept entreprises qui se faisaient concurrence.
He eventually charmed the shipwrights with his genius craftsmanship.
Mais ses techniques révolutionnaires ont su séduire les autres patrons.
Five years ago, he managed to merge all seven companies, and the rest is history.
Voilà aujourd'hui cinq ans qu'il a unifié ces sept entreprises
That's the current Galley-La Company.
et fondé Galley-La Company.
His passion and skill for shipbuilding hasn't waned,
Sa passion et son savoir-faire n'ont jamais faibli,
and he's never lost the respect of the shipwrights.
et lui valent toujours le respect des artisans.
And, because the craftsmen take pride in their skills,
Et puis, leur travail fait leur fierté,
they neither give in to pirates nor authority.
ils ne plient ni devant les pirates ni devant les autorités.
That's how we run things here.
C'est comme ça que ça fonctionne ici.
Wha...?
Hmm ?
Hey, old guy. I heard you're a top-notch shipwright.
Hé, vieux ! Alors comme ça, t'es un charpentier méga balèze ?
Wanna be a pirate with me?
Devenir pirate, ça te dit ?
Wanna run that by us again, jackass?!
Qu'est-ce que tu racontes, toi ?
H-How brazen!
Ma... Malotru !
Hey, now. He's always like this.
Allons, du calme. Il est toujours comme ça.
Sorry 'bout that.
Désolés.
Well... you guys don't have a single shipwright aboard your ship?
Si je comprends bien, vous n'avez pas de charpentier à bord ?
That's right.
Tout juste.
We came to this island to get our ship fixed and find a new crewmate.
On est venus ici
It's true that we have a whole slew of shipwrights,
Les charpentiers ne manquent pas ici,
but I wonder if any fancy the life of a pirate.
mais je ne sais pas si vous trouverez un volontaire.
If there's anyone here who's willing to sail with you, they're yours.
Si toutefois c'est le cas, je ne m'opposerai pas à son départ.
Really?! You're pretty generous! Are you sure you don't wanna come, pops?
Vraiment ?
Well, I can't. I'm the mayor.
Non, je ne peux pas. Je suis le maire de la cité.
Blow it off!
On s'en fiche de ça !
By the way, is there actually a woman named Nico Robin on your ship?
À propos, est-ce vrai qu'à bord, vous avez une certaine Nico Robin ?
There is!
Ouais. Elle a oublié d'être bête, elle.
What? Is something the matter with Robin?
Qu'y a-t-il ? Tu lui veux quelque chose ?
No.
Du tout.
I can't believe just how amazing this is!
Bon sang, c'est incroyable !
Keep that steady! Don't rush! Go slowly!
Ouais, comme ça ! Lentement et en douceur !
If we could install a cannon like that, the Merry would be more– Huh?
J'aimerais bien avoir un canon pareil sur le Vogue Merry.
Whoa! A demi-culverin!
Ouah ! Un demi-couleuvrine !
So cool! It's so long... and shiny!
La classe ! Ce qu'il est long... Il est flambant neuf, en plus.
I'd give anything to fire something like that just once.
J'aimerais bien tirer un petit coup avec !
Now's our chance.
Voilà notre chance.
It looks like it's made of copper. That must be expensive!
Il est en cuivre, non ? Il doit coûter une fortune.
I wonder if they'd let me try firing it.
Je me demande s'ils me laisseraient l'essayer ?
Oh, wait. We've now got 300 million belly.
Mais, une petite minute ! On a 300 Millions de Berrys en poche.
We can afford to buy a few of those cannons!
On doit pouvoir s'acheter un canon comme celui-là !
Hm?
Hmm ?
Wasn't someone standing there?
Tiens, il m'avait semblé voir quelqu'un.
Huh? Kaku!
Tiens, Kaku.
Where have you been?
– Où t'étais ? – J'inspectais un navire.
Ah! You're the guy from earlier!
Vous revoilà ! Vous avez vu le bateau ?
Yep, I put my eyeballs to it.
Oui, j'en ai fait le tour.
Oh, Mr. Iceburg, you're present.
Monsieur Icebarg, vous êtes là, vous aussi ?
I'm all caught up. How was it?
Tu as inspecté leur navire ? Ton verdict ?
In all honesty...
Eh bien...
Luffy! Come on down!
Luffy ! Descends, s'il te plaît !
What?! Is that true?!
Quoi ? T'es sérieux ?
If this is a lie, you'll pay!
Si tu nous mens, gare à toi !
A lie has no legs in my line of work.
Je suis un pro. Et un pro ne ment pas.
So, where's Usopp?
Tiens ? Où est passé Usopp ?
He was just over there up until a moment ago.
Il traînait par là-bas il n'y a pas cinq minutes.
Hey, you guys! Don't these cases belong to you?
Hé, vous autres ! Ces mallettes... Ce sont les vôtres, non ?
Ah! Usopp was carrying these!
Ça alors, les mallettes d'Usopp.
Yeah, they're ours.
Oui, ce sont les nôtres.
Thanks!
Merci bien.
C'mon! Where did you go, Usopp, leaving all our precious money unattended?!
Lui alors...
Money?
"L'argent" ?
Yeah! Those bags hold 200 million belly.
Ouais, y a 200 Millions dans ces mallettes.
200 million belly?!
200 Millions ?
Nice one. See ya!
Mais bien sûr. Allez, ciao.
There's no way.
N'importe quoi.
So, how much will it cost?
Bon alors, combien ça va nous coûter ?
We can pay as much as you like! We've got tons of money!
Votre prix sera le nôtre ! On est pleins aux as !
If possible, I'd like her to be stronger, have more cannons, and be faster!
Si c'est possible,
Can you also stylize the outer hull with some tasteful engravings?
Une chouette déco extérieure en prime, c'est possible ?
Could you renovate the interior as well?
Vous pouvez aussi refaire les cabines ?
Just hold your horses.
Allons, du calme.
You guys have truly been on one incredible lark after another, right?
D'après ce que j'ai vu, votre bateau a fait un sacré périple.
You bet we did! We flew into the sky and fell back down.
Je veux, ouais ! Un aller-retour dans le ciel,
We sailed up a mountain and even got skewered.
une montagne gravie et un empalement !
We've gone through quite a bit!
Il a morflé, le pauvre.
So, we'd like to have her fixed good!
Voilà pourquoi il faut lui refaire une beauté.
Her scars from battle are too deep.
Ses séquelles sont trop importantes.
Do you mean it'll take awhile to complete repairs?
Les réparations seront longues, c'est ça ?
No.
Non.
I'll give it to you straight. Your ship...
Pour être franc, votre bateau...
is beyond repair, even with our expertise.
est irréparable. On ne peut plus rien pour lui.
I'm guessing it's the keel.
La quille aussi est fichue ?
Yeah. It's taken a lot of damage.
Ouais. Elle est pas belle à voir.
No way.
C'est pas possible...
But we've been traveling just fine up until today!
Mais hier encore, il naviguait sans problème !
Let's suppose that we gave it the old college try.
Quelles que soient les réparations qu'on pourrait lui apporter,
The probability that she reaches the next island is...
ses chances d'atteindre la prochaine île...
zero.
sont nulles.
Merry, are you really...
Merry, dis-moi... C'est bien vrai ?
done sailing?
Tu ne peux plus naviguer ?
Well, crap.
Alors ça, c'est fort.
I'm sorry, Sanji. I got a little lost in the books.
Désolé.
There's no need to apologize.
T'as rien fait de mal.
I just assumed the one with Robin was you in your human form.
J'étais sûr que la personne avec Robin, c'était toi, sous ta forme humaine.
Then, who in the world was that masked man?
Du coup, je me demande bien qui était ce type au masque.
Stranger still, they suddenly disappeared.
En plus, ils ont disparu d'un coup.
Yeah. Robin's scent vanished there too.
Oui. Même l'odeur de Robin s'est complètement évaporée.
It's probably nothing, but my stomach's in a knot about this.
J'espère que ça va aller, mais je me fais un peu de bile.
Huh?
Hein ?
Do you need me to give you a checkup?
Tu veux que je t'examine ?
I'm not sick!
C'est pas une maladie !
But I feel like that Aokiji guy said something about this.
Mais ce qu'a dit Aokiji me trotte dans la tête.
So, what did he say?
Il a dit quoi, déjà ?
He kept alluding to Robin's past.
Il n'arrêtait pas de parler du passé de Robin.
He also mentioned we'd someday regret taking her on.
En disant qu'on regretterait de l'avoir accueillie à bord.
That rings a bell.
Je m'en souviens, maintenant.
But how does this relate to Robin's disappearance?
Mais tu crois que c'est lié à la disparition de Robin ?
I don't know.
J'en sais fichtre rien.
Anyway, we're getting nowhere like this. Let's go back to the Merry for now.
Pour l'instant, on ne peut rien faire. Rentrons au Merry.
If there's no problem, she'll be back soon.
Si tout va bien, elle rentrera bientôt.
Good point.
Tu as raison.
You can't fix the Merry?! Why not?!
Le Vogue Merry est irréparable ? Comment ça ?
Aren't you guys amazing shipwrights?!
Vous êtes des super charpentiers, non ?
If you need money, just look! We've more than enough!
On a tous les sous qu'il faut.
Money's not the issue.
Ce n'est pas une question d'argent.
All the money in the world can't return your ship to its original state.
Même avec tout l'argent du monde, on ne peut pas restaurer votre navire.
I'm rather surprised that your crew made it this far in a ship that's worse for the wear.
Quand je pense qu'il a tenu jusqu'ici dans un état pareil, ça force vraiment le respect.
What do you mean?! What's wrong with the Merry?!
Comment ça ? Quel est le problème du Vogue Merry ?
Do you know what the keel is, you hussy?
Tu sais ce que c'est qu'une quille, l'impudente ?
On the bottom of the ship?
C'est sous le bateau, non ?
That's right. It's the most crucial piece of wood on the ship.
Bingo.
It supports the ship from stem to stern.
C'est la partie la plus importante du bâtiment.
When you build a ship, you start off by placing the keel.
Quand on construit un navire, on commence par la quille.
Then the stem, the stern, and the frame structure—
Puis on ajoute la proue, la poupe, la coque,
that'd be the floors, futtocks, and deck beams...
les membrures, les jointures et le pont.
And you carefully position each piece of lumber around the keel.
Tous les morceaux de bois s'organisent minutieusement autour de la quille,
Shipbuilding in a nutshell.
Les navires sont faits ainsi.
The keel is the very foundation— the very essence—of a ship's framework.
Sans cette véritable moelle épinière, pas de navire.
Once it's damaged beyond repair, it can't just be replaced.
Et quand elle est trop endommagée, il est impossible de la remplacer.
In other words, replacing the keel is just building a ship from scratch.
Car cela reviendrait à refaire le bateau de A à Z.
So, no one can fix her anymore.
Voilà pourquoi personne ne peut plus rien pour lui.
Your ship is little more than scrap wood awaiting its fate.
Votre bateau, en fait, c'est juste un tas de bois à l'agonie.
Hey! Don't say it like that!
Dites donc, je vous permets pas !
Whatever. It's the truth.
Pourquoi ? C'est la vérité.
Okay then! You gotta build us a ship from scratch!
Dans ce cas, refaites-le en partant de zéro.
Build the Going Merry!
Reconstruisez le Vogue Merry.
Why not?
Et pourquoi ?
We can build a similar ship, but strictly speaking, it wouldn't be the same as before.
On peut construire un navire ressemblant,
The reality is that no two ships can ever be exactly the same.
Dans ce monde, il n'existe pas deux navires pareils.
Meaning what?!
Comment ça ?
Do any two trees in this world ever grow in exactly the same way?
As-tu déjà vu deux arbres qui poussent de la même manière ?
A seafaring vessel is mostly wood, so the size and curves of the ship are determined by the shape of the trees.
Le principal matériau d'un voilier, c'est le bois.
That's why an exact duplicate can't be built, even when using the ship's very blueprint.
Même en suivant les plans d'origine,
Even if we followed a blueprint to build such a copy,
Si on reconstruisait votre navire,
the crew who knew the old ship best would undoubtedly feel the difference.
les premiers à remarquer qu'il n'a rien à voir avec l'original,
That crew would be you guys!
ce serait vous, bien évidemment !
So, that...
Oh non...
That means we really can't sail aboard the Going Merry ever again?
Mais alors, le Vogue Merry ne peut vraiment plus naviguer ?
You got the gist of it.
C'est exactement ça.
Either sail her into a watery grave...
Vous pouvez attendre qu'il coule
or take her apart lickety split.
ou bien le désosser vous-mêmes dès maintenant.
A caravel!
Une caravelle !
Ooh! She's a great ship!
Ouah ! Sympa, le bateau !
Alright! All done!
C'est bon ! On est parés !
Our pirate ship, the Going Merry, is finally ready!
Maintenant, le Vogue Merry est prêt à partir à l'aventure !
Well... your ship has reached her end.
Que voulez-vous, il a fait son temps.
This is a good opportunity.
Voyez ça comme une bonne occasion
You need to face facts and buy a new ship.
de vous acheter un bateau neuf.
You've got money, right? And I heard correctly that your ship's a caravel?
Vous avez de l'argent, non ?
Truth be told, she's an older style of ship and wouldn't handle the journey ahead.
C'est pas avec une antiquité pareille
No. I don't intend to get a new ship.
Non, je veux pas en changer.
Luffy.
Luffy...
Our...
Notre navire...
Our ship is the Going Merry!
Notre navire, c'est le Vogue Merry !
If she's repaired, she'll sail!
Si on le répare, il pourra encore naviguer !
She'll be okay! Even today, she sailed with no problem!
Il n'est pas fini ! On est venus ici sans problème.
And now, out of nowhere, you say she's done sailing?!
Et vous, vous nous dites qu'il est condamné ?
Who would believe that?!
Pourquoi je vous croirais ?
You say this, but she's stronger than any of you know!
Vous savez pas à quel point ce navire est costaud,
So, you'd sail her until she sinks.
Tu préfères qu'il coule sous tes pieds ?
Good grief.
C'est pas croyable.
And you call yourself a ship's captain?!
Et tu te dis capitaine d'un navire ?
This discussion is over. Think about it carefully.
On va en rester là.
If you spent the 300 million here, we'd build you a state-of-the-art ship.
Pour 300 Millions, vous aurez un modèle dernier cri.
Kalifa!
Kalifa.
Here. Please look this over.
Voici notre catalogue, regardez-le.
This catalog lists new and used models. Use it as a price reference, too.
Il contient nos modèles neufs et d'occasion.
Mr. Iceburg!
Monsieur Icebarg.
You have a visitor at the gate.
Vous avez de la visite, à l'entrée du chantier.
That World Government official is here again, it seems.
On dirait encore des agents du Gouvernement.
Peepley Lulu Pitch, Blacksmithing, and Block-And-Tackle Foreman Dock One Galley-La Company
Peepley Lulu Contremaître forge et tirage de charges lourdes Quai n°1 Galley-La Company
Shall I turn him away?
Je les raccompagne ?
Well, sure thing! Tell him I'm not here.
Oui, on va faire ça. Dis-leur que je suis absent.
Anyway, you've got a bad case of bed head, Lulu.
Par contre, t'as encore un épi du tonnerre, Lulu.
Drat! Pardon me!
Ah oui, pardon. Je suis désolé.
Well then, I'll ask him to leave.
Bon, je vais les renvoyer.
Y-Yeah, would you?
Oui, s'il te plaît !
Hold it, Iceburg.
Pas si vite, Icebarg.
So you're here after all.
T'es bien là, en fait.
Hey, you guys, hide! They're government officials!
Vite, allez vous planquer ! Ce sont des agents !
What? O-Okay.
Hein ? D'accord.
Well, hello there, Corgi. I'm not here today.
Tiens, mais c'est ce bon vieux Corgy. Je ne suis pas là, aujourd'hui.
Yes, you are!
Si, t'es bien là !
Look, I came all this way by sea train.
Dire que je me suis coltiné tout le trajet en train,
Corgi World Government Official
Corgy Agent du Gouvernement Mondial
Please don't avoid me.
tu pourrais être un peu conciliant.
Hmm?
Hmm ?
What do I smell, but the scent of pirates?
J'ai l'impression que ça sent le pirate, par ici.
Of course it is. But I'm only here to chat.
Mais c'est pas le problème. Il faut qu'on cause.
I hate you! Go home!
Je t'aime pas. Du balai !
Acting like a child?
Grandis un peu.
I'm a fully grown man.
Je suis bien assez grand.
Well, then stop stalling.
Ne sois pas si borné.
You're really going to like what I have to say. Please just hear me out.
J'ai une nouvelle qui va te plaire, alors écoute-moi, au moins.
Now, let's go somewhere private.
Allons discuter dans un endroit tranquille.
They keep coming back. How persistent.
Ils sont vraiment collants.
What could they want with Mr. Iceburg?
Ils lui veulent quoi, au père Icebarg ?
It has nothing to do with us. It must be something to do with power.
Ça ne nous regarde pas, ils doivent causer politique. Rouhou.
Shall I beat them silly?
Et si on les rétamait ?
Perish the thought. They're from the World Government.
Laisse tomber, ils sont du Gouvernement Mondial.
Hm?
– Hmm ? – Quoi ? Un problème ?
I noticed something about the cases when I carried them to our hiding spot.
Depuis que j'ai soulevé les valises, y a un truc qui me gêne.
They're pretty light.
Elles sont bien légères.
What...? Why?
Hein ? Pourquoi elles seraient légères ?
Oh, don't joke like that. They couldn't be light with all that money in them.
Allons, arrête un peu.
Who was that just now?!
C'est quoi, ces cris ?
You idiots! What's the big fuss?!
Idiots, pourquoi vous gueulez ?
Hey, woman! Sitting like that lets me see...!
Hé, femme ! C'est quoi, cette pose indécente ?
Don't tell me... There's...
Bon sang... Ce n'est pas...
No way...
... possible.
Two-hundred million belly...!
Les 200 Millions !
Gone! It's really gone!
Ils ont disparu ! Vraiment disparu !
Now that I see them, these aren't even our briefcases!
En y regardant bien, ce ne sont pas nos valises !
Wh-Wh-Wh-What're we gonna do?!
On fait quoi ?
Hey, you guys! What's with the shouting?
Hé, vous ! Pourquoi vous criez ?
Our money is... gone.
L'argent a disparu.
It's... totally... gone.
Complètement... Entièrement disparu.
What?!
– Comment ? – Pauly, encore toi ?
It wasn't me!
C'est pas moi !
Truthfully?
– Vraiment ? – Pourquoi je mentirais ?
Are you for real?!
– C'est vraiment vrai ? – Ils sont bruyants. Au fait, Kaku,
Wait...! This isn't...! Just... just shut up! I swear... I'm not lying! Honestly!
t'étais pas avec la Franky Family, tout à l'heure ?
Hm? How do you mean?
Hein ? De quoi tu parles ?
I've not clapped eyes on the Franky Family all day.
Je les ai pas vus de la journée.
That sure is strange. I swear I saw your long nose among them.
C'est bizarre. Je croyais avoir reconnu ton grand nez.
Hold on a sec, you guys!
Stop ! Vous avez dit quoi ?
That's Usopp!
C'est Usopp !
He was with the Franky Family?!
Il était avec la Franky Family ?
He was with them, or rather, he was carried away by them.
On peut dire ça. Ils le traînaient derrière eux.
They kidnapped him!
C'est un enlèvement, ça !
Luffy! We need to find him quickly!
Luffy, cherchons-le en vitesse.
Okay!
Ça roule !
Hey! Wait! Where're you gonna look, Luffy?!
Attends un peu ! On ne sait même pas où chercher !
Just wait, Usopp! Money!
Je viens te chercher, Usopp ! Toi aussi, l'argent !
Hey, where's the Franky Family hideout?
Dites, où est la planque de la Franky Family ?
It's not really a hideout.
C'est pas vraiment une planque. Ils ont un chantier,
Just follow the coast northwest from Rocky Cape.
Il faut juste continuer vers le nord.
It's called the Franky House.
C'est la Franky House.
Luffy!
Luffy ?
What gives? As if he could just run off and find Usopp by himself!
Tout seul, il ne les retrouvera jamais.
Finding Luffy will have to wait.
J'ai pas le temps de chercher Luffy.
I'll take the money back to the ship for now.
Je dois d'abord déposer l'argent au navire.
Bringing 100 million with me while asking for 200 million is just begging them to take the rest.
Je ne vais quand même pas faire cadeau à ces voleurs
Anyway, yagara, please take the quickest route back to the bull shop!
Je t'en prie, Yagara, ramène-moi au plus vite chez ton patron.
Zoro and the rest of us will need to teach them a lesson!
Zoro et les autres vont leur donner une leçon.
Franky Family! Stealing from pirates was a bad decision!
La Franky Family... Voler des pirates, c'est vraiment un comble.
Welcome to level one, the Backstreets shopping district.
Niveau 1. Marché des faubourgs.
Take care and have a good day!
Faites attention en sortant.
I'm counting on you, yagara!
Je compte sur toi, Yagara.
What the heck?!
Il se passe quoi, là ?
Hey, watch out, lady!
Faites donc attention !
Sorry!
Désolée !
Usopp... Tell me you somehow got away.
J'espère qu'Usopp a réussi à leur échapper.
This is terrible.
C'est pas beau à voir.
Who the heck is he?
D'où il sort ?
Hey! Does anyone know who this guy is?!
Dites, quelqu'un connaît cet homme ?
A crowd of people...
Un attroupement ?
Wait, yagara! Stop! Stop!
Attends, Yagara. Arrête-toi un peu.
Usopp!
Usopp ?
Usopp! Wake up!
Usopp, accroche-toi !
Hey! Are you okay?!
Ça va aller ?
C'mon!
Réponds-moi.
C'mon! Usopp! Usopp!
Allez, Usopp. Usopp !
So hey, you guys wouldn't happen to be pirates?
Hé, toi. Vous seriez pas des pirates, des fois ?
Shut up! Don't just stand there gawking!
Bouclez-la ! Circulez, il n'y a rien à voir !
Usopp! Was it the Franky Family who did this to you? Was it them?!
Usopp, c'est la Franky Family qui t'a fait ça ? C'est eux ?
Yeah... I was too weak.
Oui... Je suis trop faible...
Our money...
L'argent...
they took it all.
Ils ont tout pris...
Nami...
Nami...
Yeah?
Oui ?
The crew... I can't face them.
Que vont dire les autres ? J'ai honte.
And... we were so close to having the Merry repaired.
Alors que le Merry allait enfin pouvoir être réparé...
I feel... so ashamed.
J'ai tout fait rater...
Dammit!
Bon sang...
Usopp, I get it.
Usopp, tout va bien.
Don't worry about the money. You can count on us to get it back.
Ne t'inquiète pas pour l'argent. On va aller le récupérer tous ensemble.
He's hurt pretty bad. I probably shouldn't move him.
Il est salement amoché, mieux vaut ne pas le déplacer.
Usopp, stay here for a bit.
Usopp, attends-moi ici.
I'll hurry back to the ship and get help!
Je rentre vite au navire et je ramène des renforts.
I'll bring Chopper, too, so that he can treat you!
Chopper va venir te soigner.
Please don't worry about the money!
Ne t'en fais pas pour l'argent.
I heard their hideout is just up ahead.
La planque de ces canailles n'est pas loin.
We'll crush them and put an end to this!
On va aller les défoncer.
Hey! This isn't a show!
Dites donc ! Vous n'avez pas autre chose à faire ?
Listen, Usopp. Just stay put, okay?
D'accord, Usopp ? Ne bouge surtout pas d'ici.
I'll be right back!
Je reviens tout de suite !
Get the lead out, yagara!
Plus vite, Yagara !
Ahh! A runaway bull!
Un Bull emballé !
Hey!
Hé !
And... we were so close to having the Merry repaired.
Alors que le Merry allait enfin pouvoir être réparé...
All the money in the world can't return your ship to its original state.
Même avec tout l'argent du monde, on ne peut pas restaurer votre navire.
Whether we decide to buy a new ship...
Qu'on décide d'acheter un nouveau navire
or find someone who's willing to fix and improve the Merry,
ou qu'on choisisse malgré tout de le faire réparer,
we've got to spend the entire 300 million to upgrade or get a new ship.
on doit utiliser ces 300 Millions pour avoir un meilleur navire.
The seas will only get rougher from here.
Sinon, on aura du mal pour la suite.
We definitely need that money.
On a absolument besoin de cet argent.
We have to get it back!
On doit le récupérer.
Is that true?!
C'est vrai ?
At least that's what that shipwright said.
Ouais. C'est ce qu'a dit le charpentier.
This ship...
Ce navire...
...can no longer be fixed? Even if we have the money?!
Il est irréparable ? Même en payant ?
Then, what'll happen to the Merry?!
Que va devenir le Merry, alors ?
Beats me.
J'en sais rien.
In the end, it all depends on how Luffy, Nami, and Usopp react to the assessment.
On va déjà voir comment Luffy et les autres réagissent à la nouvelle.
Those three at the shipyard will probably come up with a solution.
Comme ils sont au chantier, c'est à eux de voir.
I don't buy it. It seems really sudden.
Quand même, c'est dur à croire.
Look at the ship! She's the same old Merry.
Après tout, regardez, le navire est comme d'habitude.
From the East Blue to here, we were with Merry the whole way!
Il a fait tout le trajet entre East Blue et ici.
But that's exactly the reason.
C'est justement parce qu'il a fait ce trajet.
Humans endure hardship and become more resilient;
Les épreuves renforcent les êtres humains,
ships are different.
mais pas les navires.
They accumulate stress and damage.
Ils accumulent juste les blessures.
It's hard to swallow.
Ça me dépasse, tout ça.
Besides, how's Usopp gonna react when he hears this?
J'ose pas imaginer la réaction d'Usopp quand il entendra ça.
But, I love the Going Merry!
Moi, j'aime le Vogue Merry !
We all do. But like that guy said, her battle scars are too deep.
Tout le monde l'aime.
There's the Going Merry, but then there's Robin.
Entre le Merry et Robin, on est servis.
What a depressing afternoon.
Quel après-midi...
Guys!
Tout le monde !
Oh? Nami's back!
Tiens, Nami est rentrée.
Hm? Looks like she's alone.
Elle est toute seule, on dirait.
What happened to Luffy and Usopp?
Où sont passés Luffy et Usopp ?
Nami! Did something happen?!
Nami chérie ! Il est arrivé quelque chose ?
Water Seven Outskirts Northeast Coast Dismantlers
Démanteleurs Water Seven Périphérie Côte nord-est
Yow! Yow, yow! Did you say "200 million"?!
Yow ! Yow, yow ! 200 Millions ?
The Franky House
La Franky House
Yes, 200 million!
Oui, 200 Millions !
Whatcha think, Bro?!
C'est mortel, non ? Patron ?
Amazing! You guys are amazing!
C'est fantastique. Bien joué, les gars.
With this much cash, we can finally get the thing we've always wanted!
Avec ce joli pactole, on va enfin pouvoir acheter le truc qu'on voulait.
We did it, didn't we, Bro?
On a enfin réussi, patron.
After three long years! You'd always say, "Once I get the money..."
Ça va faire trois ans qu'on court après.
– It took so long. – Yeah.
– On s'en est donné, du mal. – Ouais.
Each time we got a chunk of money, we'd pin our hopes on yagara races...
Dès qu'on avait un peu d'argent, on le jouait aux courses de Yagaras.
– ...and end up broke!
Et on perdait tout !
Each time we captured a criminal with a bounty, we'd party it up...
Lorsqu'on empochait une prime, on allait se saouler...
– ...and end up broke!
Et on dépensait tout !
We couldn't quite save up the 200-million-belly business expense!
On n'a jamais réussi à rassembler les 200 Millions qu'il nous fallait,
But we finally got it all!
mais ils viennent de tomber du ciel !
Oh, yeah! You guys pulled through big time!
Parfait, les gars. Vous vous êtes bien débrouillés.
Well then, it ain't much, but here's five million belly.
Donc, même si c'est pas grand-chose, voici 5 Millions de Berrys.
I want to show you my appreciation, so eat, drink, and be merry!
C'est pour vous remercier. Mettez-vous-en plein la panse !
That's our Bro!
Vous êtes le meilleur, patron !
It's party time!
On va faire la fête !
Wh-What the hell?!
C'est quoi, ça ?
Hm?
Hmm ?
Aw, dammit!
Eh merde !
Who're you?! You wanna dance with the Franky Family?!
Qui ose venir chercher des noises à la Franky Family ?
Huh?! You're that string bean from earlier!
Hein ? C'est toi ? L'avorton de tout à l'heure ?
How the hell are you still standing?!
Il tient encore debout ?
Give me back the money!
Rendez-moi cet argent.
"Give me back the money"? So, you're one of Straw Hat's goons?
Tu veux qu'on te rende l'argent ?
That's right, Bro!
Oui ! C'est ça, patron !
Since he's with Straw Hat Luffy, we expected him to be a real tough pirate...
On le croyait super balèze, vu qu'il est avec Luffy au chapeau de paille.
...but it turns out he's just a weak punk!
Mais en fait, c'est une lavette.
As if you'd understand anything!
Je t'ai pas sonné, toi !
Whoa there!
Hop là !
Is he for real?!
Il joue à quoi, là ?
I'll admit you've got guts to come and get the money back all by yourself,
Tu es venu tout seul pour le récupérer, j'admire ta bravoure.
but I can't let you have it.
Mais je ne te le rendrai pas.
Give it back!
Rendez-le-moi.
We have to... have our ship repaired.
Cet argent... C'est pour réparer... notre navire.
We desperately need that money!
Cet argent est très important.
With that money, we can finally...
Avec cet argent, on va enfin...
We can finally mend the Going Merry's wounds!
Pouvoir faire réparer le pauvre Vogue Merry.
This money... I won't let you assholes take it!
Alors je vais sûrement pas vous laisser nous le prendre !
What's got you all worked up?
Allons, t'énerve pas comme ça.
I see you really love your ship.
T'as l'air de beaucoup tenir à ton navire.
Well! It doesn't matter what happens to your ship anymore.
Mais bon, ce qui peut lui arriver, c'est pas mon problème.
This money belongs to us now.
Cet argent nous appartient désormais.
Unfortunately for you, no matter what we steal from pirates, we won't be accused of committing a crime.
Malheureusement pour toi,
Let me guess! It's dirty money you stole, ain't it?
De toute façon, c'est de l'argent volé. Je me trompe ?
So, just let us keep it.
Alors, fais-toi une raison.
You could always beg the Marines for help.
Vous pouvez toujours aller pleurer auprès de la Marine,
But you'll probably be the ones arrested.
mais c'est vous qu'ils arrêteront.
It's a shame that Straw Hat Luffy...
Le plus à plaindre, c'est Luffy au chapeau de paille.
has such a useless underling who can't even guard his money.
Il est entouré d'une bande d'incapables
Guys, go ahead and show him a good time.
Je vous le laisse, faites-en ce que vous voulez.
Right now, I'm gonna take this money out for a little shopping!
Moi, je vais de ce pas faire quelques emplettes.
I can't wait!
Je vais bien m'amuser.
Not so fast!
Pas si vite !
Lethal Exploding Star!
Bille Explosive !
Remember this, long-nosed boy. My name is Franky.
Écoute-moi bien, long pif. Moi, c'est Franky.
If you want to leave this town alive, wise up and never cross me.
Et si tu veux survivre dans cette ville,
What... What're you doing?! Let go of me!
Que... Qu'est-ce que vous faites ? Lâchez-moi !
A puny weapon like this won't work on us!
Comme si un joujou pareil pouvait servir à quelque chose.
See ya, long-nose.
À la revoyure, long pif.
Thanks for the 200 million belly.
Et merci encore, pour les 200 Millions.
Stop! Give it back to me!
Attends ! Rends-moi cet argent !
Give it back!
C'est pour le Merry. Rends-le-moi !
Give it baaack!
Rends-le !
Give it... back.
Rends...
Give it... baaack!
Ren... Rends-le-moi...
Give... it... back!
Rends-le...
Give it baaaaaack!
Rends-le-moi !
I just have to hold out until Robin comes back.
Je dois tenir jusqu'au retour de Robin.
I'd just get in the way if I marched in with the others.
Les garçons s'en sortiront mieux sans moi.
And I'm scared.
Et puis, j'ai la frousse.
At any rate, I'll do anything to protect this ship and the 100 million belly.
Quoi qu'il en soit, je dois protéger ce navire et les 100 Millions.
The rest is in your hands...
Je compte sur vous, les gars.
Stop. Stop!
Stop... Stop, j'ai dit.
If I remember right, this should be the place Nami was talking about.
D'après Nami, ce devrait être par ici.
Look. This is the Backstreets shopping district.
Vous voyez ? Ça, c'est le marché des faubourgs.
You go up this canal... and here! Usopp is right here.
Il faut remonter ce canal. Et c'est là. Usopp est ici.
Okay.
D'accord.
So, Nami, where can we find these demolition workers, the Franky Family?
Nami, où se trouve le chantier de désassemblage de la Franky Family ?
Usopp!
Usopp ?
Usopp isn't here?
Il n'est pas là.
Are you sure? Maybe you screwed up the directions.
T'es sûr ? T'as dû te gourer de coin.
Look who's talking, swordsmoron!
Je suis pas comme toi, alors tais-toi !
Usopp!
Usopp ?
– What'd you say?! – Oh!
– Tu me cherches ? – Attendez...
Look! It's blood!
Regardez, c'est du sang.
That dumbass! He walked off before we got here!
Le crétin... Il est parti tout seul ?
He couldn't have, right?
Quand même pas...
Usopp.
Usopp...
Huh?
Hein ?
Help me!
Au secours !
Luffy?!
Luffy ?
What're you doing?! Where'd you come falling from?
Qu'est-ce que tu nous fais ? D'où tu déboules, comme ça ?
The shipyard...
Le chantier...
I was copying that shipwright, jumping around to look for Usopp.
Je voulais faire comme le charpentier, chercher Usopp en volant.
Are you okay?
Ça va aller ?
Yeah.
Ouais.
Oh, that's right, guys! We've got a problem!
Il faut que je vous dise, les gars !
Usopp got taken, along with the money!
Usopp et l'argent ont disparu !
Yeah, we know.
Oui, on est au courant.
Come on. We're headed to their hideout.
Viens, on va à la planque de ceux qui ont fait le coup.
They beat up Usopp and took the money.
Ils ont démoli Usopp et pris l'argent.
What?!
Hein ?
Maybe he blamed himself...
Usopp a dû culpabiliser,
and left all on his own to confront the Franky Family.
il est peut-être allé récupérer l'argent en défiant la Franky Family tout seul.
Is he breathing, Chopper?
Il respire encore, Chopper ?
He's fallen unconscious...
Il est complètement inconscient, mais il n'est pas mort.
He'll be okay. I can save him.
Ça ira. Je peux le sauver.
Just rest there a moment...
Accroche-toi encore un peu, Usopp.
We're gonna go demolish that stupid house.
On va démolir cette baraque et on revient.